Hello everybody, welcome back to IELTS Intermediate Speaking Course by PREP.
Speaking part 3 can be a bit challenging because the questions are more complex, abstract, and academic.
They require us to have certain background knowledge and ideas about different
topics and know how to organize our answers coherently.
Therefore, in today's lesson, I will guide you through a very effective
technique for brainstorming ideas in Speaking part 3.
The AEE technique, which stands for Answer, directly answer what the question is asking.
Explanation, provide an explanation for the answer.
And an example, give an example to support the answer.
Let's use the AEE technique to brainstorm ideas for the question.
Is money always the most important thing when choosing a job?
Have you finished?
Let's see how I brainstorm ideas for this question.
First, I answer the question directly.
Money is the most important factor.
However, if we only give such a short answer, it won't be
convincing and may affect the fluency and coherence score in your answer.
In addition, short answers don't allow us to use very grammar structures
and vocabulary, which can affect the lexical resource and grammatical range and accuracy scores, right?
So I'm going to add an explanation to my answer.
It ensures a comfortable and happy life.
Next, to use more vocabulary and make my answer more persuasive, I will provide an example as well.
It helps fulfill essential personal needs, such as housing, medical expenses, and nourishment.
Now, do you understand the AEE technique better?
Let's continue with the same question.
Is money always the most important thing when choosing a job?
I'll give you a different viewpoint using the AEE technique, but in a more advanced way.
Ready?
A. Answer.
Money is important, but for the career options that already offer a
satisfactory income, other factors should carry equal weight.
Then, I'm going to give an explanation.
Money is vital to meet essential personal needs, but I have another
explanation to reinforce my answer, so here's the second one.
A large paycheck can never compensate for an unfulfilling job.
Now, I'll give an example.
In Japan, many people might earn a high salary, but still feel unhappy.
From these two ways of answering, we can see that we don't
have to follow the exact order, from answer to explanation, then example, so feel free to use them in any order.
It's just a guide for us to brainstorm ideas and give us more detailed and convincing answers.
Now, let's try brainstorming another question related to career choice.
Which jobs would you say are the most respected in your country?
I'll give you 20 seconds to brainstorm ideas for this question, using the AEE technique.
20 seconds, starting now.
Have you finished?
Here is my answer.
A, answer, doctor.
E1, explanation, requires extensive education, training, professional capacity.
Example one, it takes six years to complete a medical degree and
two to four years of internship to become a general practitioner.
Explanation two, play an important role in safeguarding public health.
Example two, in the COVID-19 pandemic, many capable doctors have successfully
identified the symptoms, enabling timely treatment.
We should also note that the AEE technique is not the only
way to brainstorm ideas for speaking part three questions, but it is
a highly effective technique that helps us stay on track.
With this approach, you only need to write down the main ideas
to help structure your thoughts and save you time.
All right, now we are well prepared to enter the IELTS speaking exam room.
Let's go.
Now let's apply the AEE technique to some other questions in IELTS speaking part 3.
I really encourage you to come up with your own ideas using
the AEE technique, just like you are in the exam room, without any help.
However, if any question seems too difficult, you can answer by using my suggestions first.
Then pause the video and think of your own ideas to give a complete answer.
Are you ready?
If you're not ready yet, you can pause this video for a
while to prepare.
But remember, in the real exam, you won't have time to prepare.
How do people spend their leisure time in your country?
I'll give you 10 seconds to brainstorm.
10 seconds starts now.
Finished?
Here's my outline.
In our country, people like indoor activities.
Because they're inexpensive, not physically demanding, and can suit any personality and preference.
For example, there are various free genres of books and types of games available for people to enjoy at home.
The second question is, is it important for people to have time for leisure activities?
You have 10 seconds to brainstorm your ideas.
10 seconds starts now.
Finished?
Here's my outline.
Firstly, I answer, yes, it is important.
Then I provide the first explanation, which is having time for leisure activities allows me to unwind.
Next, I continue to explain that leisure activities also help facilitate personal growth.
Finally, I provide an example to support the second explanation, which is how reading books can expand one's knowledge.
Good job, everyone.
Let's move on to the last question.
What types of leisure activities may become more popular in the future?
You have 10 seconds to brainstorm your ideas.
10 seconds starting now.
Finished?
Here's my outline.
First, I provide an answer that outdoor pastimes may become more popular in the future.
Then I provide the first explanation, people becoming more health conscious,
leading to a growing demand for outdoor activities that promotes physical fitness.
Then I provide an example to support this explanation, such as activities like jogging and hiking.
Finally, I provide another explanation to further clarify the answer, which is
that outdoor activities may become popular due to the stress of modern desk jobs.
Do you remember what AEE stands for?
We've also applied all the knowledge learned today in the IELTS Speaking Part 3 test.
Don't forget to review this lesson and finish all the exercises.
Till next time, everybody.
Bye-bye.